[SPEAKER_01]: Ajahn, I want to let go of my opinions, because I see how arguing about who is right causes me problems and stress.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I often just end up adopting a new, so-called better view, to replace the old one, which just creates a new source of friction with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Political, religious, weather, diets, exercises, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I actually hold a view without having it cause internal tension due to being in conflict with opposing views?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if not, how can I not hold to any view at all?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that even possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think the whole question is based on the premise that the view is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is that they can't not
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot argue.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't restrain their speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yes, it's impossible to just choose to not hold any views, because you'll be holding that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you described, what the question described, means, like, the views is not the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: The issue is that that person can't help themselves but argue about the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you restrain your speech and don't argue about your views, then what's the conflict?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you, like, you're attached to your view of... Well, you are attached to your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: View means the existential standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like, oh, I can impartially hold a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you are invested in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, sometimes more, sometimes less, but view is not a... holding a view, it's not a neutral thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could say, oh, holding a view is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you could also say non-restraint is a root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you can hold the views, other people can hold their views, but there will be no conflict for as long as you don't act out of your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either through argument or trying to change other people's behavior and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to avoid the conflict, avoid the disruption, restrain your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't talk about your views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you have a view, then, about whatever it is, say, a political view, you think is right, and you hear an opposing view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not get... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's still not the source of conflict.
[SPEAKER_00]: The conflict begins when you start acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always going to be things that are displeasing to you in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're either going to take that for granted and then try and change the world,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you're gonna recognize that, okay, I have to draw a line somewhere for my mind and then not not act out to the extent that would be actually causing conflict and adding further passion and discomfort and suffering on account of already existing, say, discrepancies between what I believe and what others believe.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, after, like, say, when you are not adding more fuel to those things, you could, eh... pretty much, like, through the same type of training that we often describe, eh... reduce even the mental involvement, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the mental proliferation, mental choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would be adding, say, to the views and to the weight of those views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, even if you hear the opposing views, like, you would not be affected emotionally as much as before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you learn how not to be invested in your views emotionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that development of non-investment in your views emotionally can only begin if you stop acting out of the investment in your views emotionally, which is speaking out of your views, arguing with your views, defending your views, you know, proving others wrong and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that has to be subdued first, so that you can get to the source of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the way the question was formulated implies that, oh, yeah, there is conflict, there is suffering when I meet the opposed views, and then everything that arises from it, and, you know, you argue, and you this, and the disagreements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, if only I could not have views, then everything would be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, like, true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything would be fine when you go beyond views, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: when you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to get that, you have to stop making it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through speaking out of your views, or doing this out of your views, or doing that out of your views.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that, there's that one attempt or one view that tries to get free from all views and free from the suffering that comes, that's around holding views.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attempt of, well, I don't hold to any views and everything's... every view is just, okay, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just go with whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that is a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, as I said, a desperate attempt to find a way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or I don't say, I don't agree with, or I don't disagree with your view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, trying to maintain neutrality as a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which can only go so far, because that is your view that you depend on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody challenges that neutrality, which it will be challenged sooner or later, you'll see that you still very much hold the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just try to, as I said, retroactively convince yourself that, I don't hold to any views, or I'm practicing non-holding to any views.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it comes out of opposition too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes as a response to the actual discomfort that arises on account of your views that you hold.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't just, as I said, paste the wishful thinking on your mind and say, don't hold to any views, because that very much is going to be something that you hold.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you still believe it isn't, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: If that were true, then you would be going throughout your day, days, not upset, not moved by sensual desire, not moved by irritation.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those are symptoms of holding existential positions that are contradictory, that are wrong, that are discrepant, that are based on greed, aversion, destruction and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people, as I said, people can say that they don't hold to any fixed views, but what does your practice and life around tell you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is the mind coming up with stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you very much hold to your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And preferences, like... Of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want the dishes to be washed in a certain way, at a certain time, with a certain method, and then someone doesn't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all of those are views, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, suttas, when they were sort of boiled down to these, like, extremely genetic stock passages that we have today, lost all the nuances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we read those parts, when it says, oh, here is someone in Brahman, goes and kind of withdraws himself physically from centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, they start holding views.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the usual translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: They start arguing about, is the world eternal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the world not eternal?
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people think it's like some sort of optional, abstract, metaphysical debate that monks will start having suddenly when they live with drawn-from-desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was just a genetic phrase.
[SPEAKER_00]: to refer to the utmost kind of endpoints of all sorts of views that you can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all the views will boil down to you either believe you're going to live forever or you believe everything is material and there is no afterlife and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But practically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much any preference, any standpoint, would fall within the scope of eternalism and annihilationism in the in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even people, they don't think about whether their self is real or whether they will live after death or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: They fall into these categories.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Brahmachala Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are like the net of views that come from the source of, like, it's either this or this, and from there you get two, from two you get four, eight, sixteen, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when when people read that sutta about holding the views, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, when you live withdrawn from sensuality, and we've seen that in the monasteries, when you live withdrawn from sensuality, everything else becomes very important.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did you put that broom?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you turn around?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you change the knob on the this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I told you not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: I told you to put a latch this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it becomes like immediate kind of like mental sort of visceral reaction to all these little preferences.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people believe, oh, but I don't hold to any views, but here I am annoyed by every little thing, or provoked by every little thing that's not to my liking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, that's already... those are the views, and those are the views because of which then samanas and brāhmaṇas start to fall out and argue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, we... that's not how we wrap the rope here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, those sandals are technically too long of the laces and you must have this... Look at the whole commentaries in the vinaya and the subsequent kind of arguments that were kind of canonized.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of just like absolute, complete loss of perspective, proliferation, you know, like the... Acting out of use.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all born...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all, exactly, it all comes acting out of views, because now that becomes your main preoccupation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the training is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stopped acting out of core sensuality, well, now stop acting out of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now it's becoming a bit more personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, okay, you know, I keep the precepts, I live in the monastery and so on, but then you have, yeah, these views that nag you the whole day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you know, I told him six times to put the shoes in the rack, and he still doesn't put it in the rack.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's obviously your view, your standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: What should be done?
[SPEAKER_00]: You acted out, because obviously you perceive some sort of authority, because you're more senior or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It didn't happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now it's adding more to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, is he disrespecting me now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is he doing that out of disrespect?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind gets even more involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you do the same as before?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I'm wanting... because this is now the coarse level, so I'll stop fueling it first to get to the bottom of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I take it for granted and justify it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, no, I have to do it, because if he doesn't do it, everybody else will do it, and then the monastery will look like crap, and then we gotta fix it, and we gotta...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like views, and you fell into a trap of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there, you see that you're holding that view?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see you being... you're triggering... Well, that's exact.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I know if I hold the view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, is there an emotional response to the opposing view, to the opposing idea, to the opposing preference?
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is an emotional response, means you are holding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what do you need to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is not act out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not add more to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you begin.
[SPEAKER_00]: By speech, through actions, not taking for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: When then the mind is subdued on that, like, as I said, more refined from the core sensuality level, then it's like, as I said, the space opens up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it's like, okay, I do have a preference.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a challenge to preference.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I can actually maintain the perspective in regard to both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't matter if that challenge remains for one day, two days, three days, six months.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perspective is unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: Container remains there, holding it both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, actually, I'm not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I do have a preference, but I'm not holding to a view that's implicit in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't just start with that, while you're still undermining it through your actions and your speech and so on, and justifying doing so.